Jason Flatman here and in today's
edition we're going to talk about a
rhetorical device or a common language
tactic that's used mostly to incite
outrageousness or righteous indignation
and to hijack critical thinking. Uh it's
either used to appeal to a base of
people, to rally them up, to do what you
want them to do, uh or to make the other
side look worse than it is if you are
doing an us versus them type of attack
or if you're positioning somebody else
or some other ideology or concept to be
worse off than you. Now, this is
unfortunate because this tactic, this
language communication device can be
incredibly powerful if used in certain
situations or for certain um outcomes.
though it's very rarely used this way.
It's mostly used as a weapon. And even
the word weapon is an exact example of
what I'm talking about here. What am I
talking about? I'm talking about loaded
language. Uh it's one of the many labels
of linguistics that they call it. They
can call it emotive language or
emotionally charged language. Uh but
whatever you want to call it, I like to
think of it as loaded language. It's
words or phrases that are designed to
elicit strong emotional responses.
And some of the ones that are most
common that have entered our vernacular,
especially at least in the United
States, come from politicians cuz they
are the best at it. And by the way, it
crosses the aisle. It doesn't matter
Republican, Democrat, uh the the the
most right or the most left, whatever
the case may be, they are master at
loaded language. So if you ever want to
study loaded language, you can get a
free education just by opening up the
newspaper. So let me give you some ideas
of what loaded language is. The word
terrorist is a very loaded word whether
it's accurate or not sometimes and
oftent times the way the word is used is
to create that emotional response. Uh
same thing with torture or freedom or
fascism or socialism and in in certain
circles the word capitalism is a loaded
word. So some of this is contextual. Now
uh my favorite example in terms of
technique forget about outcome or what
it did or didn't accomplish. put
ideology aside for a second and put on
the learning hat, right? Uh the the
death tax is probably the greatest
example. And the gentleman, the
strategist, the political strategist
that came up with it, his name escapes
me right now, wrote a book on this
concept, um using this language. And
what they did is they repositioned the
estate tax, which was like a coin flip.
It could be voted for or against uh
increasing it or doing something with
it. And when they branded it as the
death tax, that loaded language freaks
people out. And so people that normally
that were for the estate tax became very
much against the death tax. Uh even
changing something like affordable care
act to Obamacare uh is a way to load
that because to certain groups of people
that word represents or that name
represents a very loaded emotional
knee-jerk reaction. Patriot Act is a
fantastic example of who's against
patriotism. Patriotism evokes a very
strong positive emotion. A lot of loaded
language will evoke negative emotions in
the sense of of things like the war on
drugs is a fantastic loaded phrase as if
we're actually fighting a war with drugs
and they got their artillery and they're
shooting at us and we're ducking and
covering and coming back at them. Uh
kind of stuff. Most of this is negative,
loaded language, but there are some
positive uh like the Patriot Act um was
a very loaded term u that evokes a
certain emotional response that doesn't
necessarily
help with discourse about the pros and
cons of such an act. Uh fake news is
probably the most popular one right now.
Um it's a very loaded concept
um in terms of it it evokes a certain
emotional response. Uh to categorically
call something fake news is is going to
incite certain groups. It's going to
rally other groups. Uh and even certain
things on how we try to empower
ourselves to use a lot of language
because there's positive ways you can
use. I'm going to explore a couple with
you um actually in this video here. But
a very positive or attempt at positive
that I don't think ends up working is
the battle against cancer or the fight
against cancer or I'm gonna beat cancer
as if it's hand-to-hand combat. Um there
are, you know, you got to ask yourself
with anything in life I've discovered is
does this empower me or does this limit
me? It helps me move out of this
modality of this does this hurt or does
this harm me? Is this good or is this
bad? Is this evil or is this whatever?
Right? Um, it's a it's a less
judgmental, easier to assess and empower
like does this empower me or not. So,
god forbid I ever get cancer or somebody
that I love gets can cancer, I would
literally consider the language that we
use around that because it's going to
affect how we feel. If you're if you're
fighting something, there's this
implication that it's it's going to be a
blood bath. People are going to get
hurt. Something's going to have to
happen. Uh, but if you're coming up with
a plan to be as healthy as you possibly
can, regardless of whether you have
cancer or not, it probably would elicit
a different response, probably a more
thoughtful uh and a and a more
empowering response, at least for me,
than fighting or battling or war. And
you're going to discover a lot of loaded
language comes along military terms.
Okay. Now, here's a fun exercise. I
don't know if fun is the word for you,
but it's fun for me because it helps
increase my learning. helps me
understand what is loaded language, what
are options if I were to need to use
loaded language, and how can I become
more resistant to loaded language that's
designed to manipulate me or at least
understand what it is so I don't have it
just take over uh my emotions so I can
still keep kind of some sort of balance
in my life. Uh I opened up some of the
most common news sources, their
websites, and I did it across all
political spectrums. So, it's not that
one does it and the other doesn't do it.
Uh, everybody does it. And really, it's
symptomatic of a greater thing is if
your goal as the press is to sell
clicks, which is the goal of every
single press that exists out there, uh,
that's their business model. Um, then
they employ these techniques to maximize
their profits. It's as simple as that
because that's how powerful and
persuasive loaded language can be. So,
let me just share with you. And it and
it's funny because I saw these same
words repeated across all spectrums and
all across all of the most popular press
that exists out there regardless of
political leanings. Here are some words
that I found and this took me less than
15 minutes. Criminal and not in the
sense like what a criminal is. A
criminal used to describe a situation
that's probably not a criminal
situation. Loser literally calling
somebody a loser uh which evokes a
certain emotional response immediately
lashes out. Uh what's the difference
between lashing out at something and
just being uh upset at something? One
creates emotional response more than
another. A meltdown. Meltdown is a
rarely a case where something actually
is melted down, but it's a it creates a
very interesting picture. Immediately
when you hear a meltdown, you probably
think temper tantrum. Um which is kind
of a loaded term. uh bashes, cajjol,
fires back, dirty little secret,
ravages, attacks, uh please, please,
please, please, or you know, even
undercuts uh in certain context is
emotionally charged, left hanging. This
person was left hanging uh evokes some
very dark imagery if you think about it
in terms of hanging and where that
originally comes from or harm. Even even
words like, you know, harassed. There
are certain times where that word makes
sense, but other times where it's an
emotionally charged word used in a
different context. Uh, blasts,
firepower, ratchets, collapses, soarses,
fights, and battles. I see all that over
and over again. Doomed. Doomed is a
really powerful emotionally charged. And
it doesn't have to be a word. It can be
a phrase like teetering on the edge. Uh,
on the brink of destruction or on the
brink of whatever, right? These are all
concepts that they make for interesting
headlines. They definitely draw
attention. They will get opens. They
will get clicks. Uh they can help you be
persuaded or persuasive, I should say.
Uh but oftent times they are not
actually accurate of the situation.
Uh they create emotional responses to
the situation, but they are not
necessarily the most accurate way to
look at a situation and assess it and
say, "Okay, now that I understand this
information, how do I proceed with it?"
or now that I've experienced this,
what's the best way for me to proceed?
Right? So, loaded language. Now, here's
why it's important that you know this
because it's everywhere. Uh it's the
invisible thing that's simultaneously
everywhere you look. And when you become
more conscious of it, then you can be
more likely to use it or have it used
upon you when it can help you and less
likely to be manipulated with it when
you don't realize how you're being
manipulated. where you might make
decisions that you otherwise wouldn't
make if loaded language wasn't
surrounded by that. Uh so actually a
very positive manner in which I like to
use loaded language is and you got to
you got to practice this and get good at
this is if it is persuasive and it can
be emotionally charged. It's a simple
question. Um what do I need to persuade
myself to do that I want to do and
what's an emotion that if I charged it
would make me feel good and empower me
to do that. So, that is a fantastic way
in which to use loaded language in your
own personal life to help you when
you're looking at a situation that you
want to like go in on but you're having
trouble even getting started with. Um,
the other way that you want to be aware
of loaded language is when you see it,
observe it and say, "If I had to replace
this with a less loaded word, what would
that word be? And would that be as
accurate, if not more accurate, than the
loaded word itself?" Uh, so that's
really helpful and the more you do that,
the better you're going to discover that
you're able to see situations and not
just be at the mercy of being outraged
because oftent time loaded language is
going to draw up these emotions that
don't make us feel good if we keep
accessing them over and over again. So
you could say, "Oh, you got me, but now
let me look a little further." You know,
was that a full-on meltdown or was that
just a disagreement?
I don't know. Uh and lastly, there is
going to be times when you're going to
have to be persuasive, uh where there's
a lot on the line. And so to have this
in your toolkit that you can reach into
and say to the degree that I feel
comfortable, that I feel ethical with
using this loaded language, it is a uh
rhetorical device. It's a tool that I
can employ and use if I have to win over
someone or some ones to my position
because there's so much writing on the
line. It's also important to know that
if if you're in a situation like in in a
marketplace, I always look at it this
way, like my what are my competitors
doing and how am I going to position
myself against my competitors so I can
stand out, I can get attention, that I'm
not allowing other people to position me
into a corner that I shouldn't be in or
to downplay what I do to try to upplay
what they do, right? uh how what are the
weapons? There's your load of word for
you. Uh that they're using in their
communication and do I have to
neutralize them? Do I have to counteract
them? Or can I take them, finesse them,
apply them at a higher level so that way
I look better in front of my customers
than they do? It's so that's a very
specific example how you can use this.
But regardless, if you do nothing else,
here's what I would love for you to do
in this video, uh, when it's over with,
is go out there, pull up news sites,
pull up ones you love, pull up ones you
hate, and just look at the words in the
headlines and try to write down what are
the emotionally loaded words. This will
bring consciousness, and now that'll
allow you to access more uh, powerful
persuasive words when you need to in
your next form of communication, but
also make you aware of when others are
using it to you. And you can see is it
in my best interest to buy into this
loaded language or should I use this
filter and then help me understand
what's really going on and not be at the
mercy so much of having others come by
and tweak your emotions and put you in
states that you necessarily don't want
to be in. So there you go. Loaded
language. Have off with it. Leave a
comment if you've noticed loaded
language in your life that has been
really empowering or or a loaded
language that once you removed it that
was better off for you. Drop me a
comment there. Like and subscribe and
I'll talk with you